<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE feature_key_file [
   <!ELEMENT feature_key_file (comments, feature+)>
   <!ELEMENT comments (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT feature (name, description?, is_sequential, parallel_dimensions)>
   <!ELEMENT name (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT description (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT is_sequential (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT parallel_dimensions (#PCDATA)>
]>

<feature_key_file>

   <comments></comments>

   <feature>
      <name>Prevalence of Most Common Pitch</name>
      <description>Fraction of notes that correspond to the most common pitch.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Prevalence of Most Common Pitch Class</name>
      <description>Fraction of notes that correspond to the most common pitch class.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Relative Prevalence of Top Pitches</name>
      <description>Relative frequency of the second most common pitch in the piece, divided by the relative frequency of the most common pitch.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Relative Prevalence of Top Pitch Classes</name>
      <description>Relative frequency of the of the second most common pitch class in the piece, divided by the relative frequency of the most common pitch class.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Interval Between Most Prevalent Pitches</name>
      <description>Absolute value of the difference (in semitones) between the pitches of the two most frequently occurring pitches.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Interval Between Most Prevalent Pitch Classes</name>
      <description>Absolute value of the difference (in semitones) between the pitches of the two most frequently occurring pitch classes.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Number of Common Pitches</name>
      <description>Number of pitches that account individually for at least 9% of all notes. Enharmonic equivalents are grouped together for the purpose of this calculation.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Pitch Variety</name>
      <description>Number of pitches that occur at least once in the piece. Enharmonic equivalents are grouped together for the purpose of this calculation.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Pitch Class Variety</name>
      <description>Number of pitch classes that occur at least once in the piece. Enharmonic equivalents are grouped together for the purpose of this calculation.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Range</name>
      <description>Difference in semitones between the highest and lowest pitches.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Most Common Pitch</name>
      <description>MIDI pitch value of the most frequently occuring pitch.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Mean Pitch</name>
      <description>Mean MIDI pitch value, averaged across all pitched notes in the piece. Set to 0 if there are no pitched notes.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Importance of Bass Register</name>
      <description>Fraction of notes between MIDI pitches 0 and 54.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Importance of Middle Register</name>
      <description>Fraction of notes between MIDI pitches 55 and 72.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Importance of High Register</name>
      <description>Fraction of notes between MIDI pitches 73 and 127.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Most Common Pitch Class</name>
      <description>The pitch class that occurs most frequently compared to other pitch classes. A value of 0 corresponds to C, and pitches increase chromatically by semitone in integer untis (e.g. a value of 2 would mean that D is the most common pitch class). Enharmonic equivalents are treated as a single pitch class.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Dominant Spread</name>
      <description>Largest number of consecutive pitch classes separated by perfect 5ths that each individually account for at least 9% of the total notes in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Strong Tonal Centres</name>
      <description>Number of isolated peaks in the fifths pitch histogram that each individually account for at least 9% of all notes in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Major or Minor</name>
      <description>Whether the piece is major or minor, as indicated by the first encountered major/minor metadata tag in the piece. Set to 0 if the metadata indicates that the piece is major, or set to 1 if the metadata indicates that it is minor. Defaults to 0 if the key signature is unknown.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Glissando Prevalence</name>
      <description>Number of pitched MIDI Note Ons that have at least one MIDI Pitch Bend associated with them, divided by the total number of pitched Note Ons in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Average Range of Glissandos</name>
      <description>Average range of MIDI Pitch Bends, where "range" is defined as the greatest value of the absolute difference between 64 and the second data byte of all MIDI Pitch Bend messages falling between the Note On and Note Off messages of any note in the piece. Set to 0 if there are no MIDI Pitch Bends in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Vibrato Prevalence</name>
      <description>Number of pitched notes that have associated MIDI Pitch Bend messages change direction at least twice in connection with the note in question, divided by the total number of pitched Note Ons in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Microtone Prevalence</name>
      <description>Number of pitched notes that are each associated with exactly one MIDI Pitch Bend message, divided by the total number of pitched Note Ons in the piece. Set to 0 if there are no pitched Note Ons in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Most Common Melodic Interval</name>
      <description>Number of semitones corresponding to the most frequently occurring melodic interval.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Mean Melodic Interval</name>
      <description>Mean average (in semitones) of the intervals involved in each of the melodic intervals in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Distance Between Most Prevalent Melodic Intervals</name>
      <description>Absolute value of the difference (in semitones) between the most common and second most common melodic intervals in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Vertical Interval Histogram</name>
      <description>A feature vector consisting of bin magnitudes of the vertical interval histogram described in the jSymbolic manual. Each of the bins is associated with a different vertical pitch interval, and is labeled with the number of semitones in that corresponding interval. More specifically, these are numbered from 0 (a unison) to 127 (a vertical interval of 127 semitones). The magnitude of each bin is found by going through a recoding MIDI tick by MIDI tick and noting all vertical intervals that are sounding at each tick, as well as the MIDI velocities of the pair of notes involved in each vertical interval. The end result is a histogram that indicates which vertical intervals are present, and how significant these vertical intervals are relative to one another, with a weighting based on both MIDI velocity and the aggregated durations with which each interval is held throughout the piece. Finally, the histogram is normalized.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>128</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Average Number of Simultaneous Pitches</name>
      <description>Average number of pitches sounding simultaneously. Rests are excluded from this calculation. Unisons are also excluded from this calculation, but octave multiples are included in it.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Chord Duration</name>
      <description>Average duration in seconds of a chord. A "chord" here is considered to stay the same as long as no new pitch classes are added, and no pitch classes are taken away. This "chord" may consist of any number of pitch classes, even only one. A "chord" is not considered to end if it is split by one or more rests (although the rests themselves are not counted in the duration of the "chord").</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Seventh Chords</name>
      <description>Fraction of all simultaneously sounding pitch groups that are dominant seventh, major seventh or minor seventh chords. This is weighted by how long pitch groups are held (e.g. a pitch group lasting a whole note will be weighted four times as strongly as a pitch group lasting a quarter note).</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Complex Chords</name>
      <description>Fraction of all simultaneously sounding pitch groups that contain more that four pitch classes. This is weighted by how long pitch groups are held (e.g. a pitch group lasting a whole note will be weighted four times as strongly as a pitch group lasting a quarter note).</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Rhythmic Variability</name>
      <description>Standard deviation of the beat histogram bin magnitudes</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Average Note Duration</name>
      <description>Average duration of notes (in seconds).</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Initial Tempo</name>
      <description>Tempo in beats per minute at the start of the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

</feature_key_file>